on this video we are going to talk about
one of the best things you can do for
your career as a developer and that is
building side projects
Nicolas imida and my mission for this
video is to convince you to start your
side project and to help you finish it
so first let me tell you the reason why
you should start a side project today
and then I will show you how to finish
what you start by avoiding the mistakes
I made building a side project will help
you no matter what level you're on as a
developer if you are a beginner making a
side project is the ultimate way of
learning by doing it is also the only
way I found to escape from tutorial
Health tutorial hell is where many
people that are learning to code get
stuck they find themselves taking course
after course without feeling good enough
or ready to start a project on their own
I I've been there when I was learning to
code I did feel like I could follow
tutorials and books but I always felt
paralyzed when I had to start a project
from zero by myself with no one to hold
my hand looking at an empty file that I
was supposed to fill with my code now
this happens because we have a voice in
our head that tells us that we don't
know enough yet that we are not ready
the best way to know if that voice is
correct or not is to build something if
that voice is correct if you actually
don't know enough by building something
you will know what you don't know and if
that voice is incorrect that means that
you are just lacking self-confidence and
it's time to move on to the next level
if you are not a beginner anymore and
now you feel ready to go out and look
for a job having 10 cool side projects
will look better than just having
certificates and a college degree if
there is a company you want to go to you
can build side projects related to the
company and what you would like to do
for them if you you want to be a
front-end developer then maybe clone the
company's website but make it better
give it a redesign and make it load
faster if you want to be a mobile
developer build an app related to the
company its products or its users and if
you want to be a freelancer build
projects that you would like to get
hired to make or if you want to be a
backend developer you can simulate the
design of an API and database models of
a big startup let your code speak for
you if you already have a job you still
need to build side projects as we know
this industry moves at the speed of
light and you my friend need to be up to
date a side project gives you the
perfect opportunity to try technologies
that you are curious about to try a new
programming language or to use and
evaluate a new database it gives you
room to feel like a beginner again it
keeps you humble it puts you out of your
comfort zone and who knows maybe it
would allow you to change your job or
learn something that will give you a
promotion it will also make you wear
different hats you might have to do
design maybe you will learn about
deploying Security customer service you
will grow as a person as well building
an idea from start to publishing it will
teach you a lot and lastly the reason
why you should build side projects no
matter what level of developer you are
is because it reminds you how cool your
job is we can build something out of
nothing and we don't have to ask anyone
for permission to do it you don't need a
license or a permit from the government
to make something and publish it there
isn't a middleman never in the history
of the world creativity has been this
permissionless and Unbound you can
literally start a company from your
couch if you already have an idea that
you want to make awesome but if you
don't don't worry the beautiful thing
about site projects is that you can make
them as big small serious or silly as
you want if you need ideas of something
to make see if you can scratch your own
itch this means don't worry about
building something that millions of
people are going to use build something
that you and maybe your friends and
family need now my family is fairly big
I have lots of uncles and cousins and
it's hard to keep track of all of their
birthdays so I built a tiny bot that
every day checked to see if it was
someone's birthday and if it was it
would send an SMS message to all the
family telling them whose birthday it
was that is just an example and I'm sure
you will be able to find an idea like
that around you in no time and also
don't worry if your side project idea
already exists it does not have to be
unique if there is a similar product out
there you can learn from it and improve
it it is also a very good sign if you
have an idea but someone built it first
that means that your idea is actually
useful for older people which means you
have a high chance of getting real users
I did that once there is a side project
I made that is an improvement of an
already existing product just a bit
different and it's actually earning a
few dollars every month so if I
convinced you to start your side project
now is when the hard part comes which is
actually finishing it starting something
telling people you're starting something
going to Starbucks and taking a photo
with your laptop in an ice Americano
that is the easy part the hard part is
to complete what you started which is
where I have failed countless times and
I would like to share some of your
mistakes so you can avoid them the
biggest mistake I always make is being
too ambitious with the idea I want to
make the scope of the project is
directly related to the chances of you
not finishing it the bigger the scope is
the more features you plan and the
bigger the chances of you not finishing
the project are take an idea and reduce
it to its most basic features and mbb a
minimum viable product leave only the
features that are required for the app
to be able to work now do this
especially with your first site project
it is very easy to lose focus and
motivation so you need to help yourself
finish your projects by not being too
ambitious with what you want to build
instead make a list of all the features
you would like your project to have and
make a promise to yourself that after
you finish the project and if it gets 50
users then you will Implement those
features another mistake I make and the
reason why my computer is a graveyard of
Unfinished projects is not having a
deadline personally if I don't have a
deadline I don't get any work done so I
have to come up with an artificial
deadline something that gives me a sense
of urgency a date when things need to be
published and done having a deadline
also allows you to make a schedule to
plan ahead to know what kind of code you
should be writing today a very good way
to push yourself to finish your projects
is to join a hackathon an event where
you will meet like-minded people that
are Builders like you that need to
launch and finish before the hackathon
ends I still remember my first hackathon
and it was an amazing experience you can
join a physical hackathon or a virtual
one the point is to feel the peer
pressure of knowing that there are other
people working next to you and other
teams competing against you usually
hackathons also have a price so it's
also nice to know that you could
potentially be getting paid to build
your side product they also bring
exposure to you and your project you
might also be able to form a team and
launch a startup for real if you can't
find a hackathon then throw one yourself
find five co-workers or friends order
some pizza rent an office start Friday
and finish Sunday that brings me to
another thing that will help you finish
your ideas faster and that is having a
team made if you build an idea on your
own it is hard to find the motivation to
keep going sometimes this happens to me
a lot but if you have a teammate you can
motivate each other and you will find
yourself finishing the project because
you want to let the other person down
and last but not least something that
really helped me finish what I was
building is not talking about what I am
building sometimes talking about what
you are going to do and how you're going
to do it gives you a false sense of
accomplishment many people create a
GitHub page for their project they take
the coding at Starbucks photo they
choose the name for the project and they
even buy the.com domain even before they
write a single line of code most people
that do this including me don't actually
finish what they start because after the
Instagram pics and the.com domains come
the long days of code that are not
glamorous at all it's better to be quiet
and build in silence rather than being
noisy and having nothing to show for at
the end end of the day I hope that after
this video you feel inspired to start
your side project and I also hope that
you can finish and launch your project
and avoid the mistakes I made as I
mentioned before joining a hackathon is
an amazing way of building a product
practicing your skills and potentially
winning prizes for you and your team
this is why the sponsor of this video
appetizer wants to invite you to a free
hackathon the project of the hackathon
is to build a project utilizing the open
apis from appetizer.kr appetizer is a
platform where you can find all kinds of
apis for your projects they are like an
API aggregator currently they have 120
apis like text to video open banking
Healthcare data translation phase
recognition electronic contracts
payments among many others the hackathon
is organized with the help of the Korean
government and neighbor Cloud you can
register as an individual or as a team
of up to 5 people the total price pool
for for the event is twenty seven
thousand dollars and you can also
receive mentoring from the companies
that make the apis themselves
registration is open until October 7th
so click the link below to register
right now thank you for watching see you
on the next one bye